Paul Hoffman Papers
Paul Hoffman Papers
1920-1953
Hoffman, Paul.
4.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American novelist, poet, short story author (1906-1960). Born in Utica, N.Y. Correspondence (1920-1953); manuscript novels, stories, poems; a journal (1929-1930); published book reviews, poems, and stories by Hoffman; juvenilia and class notes; and photographs.
149058
Biographical History
Paul Hoffman was an American author. He wrote poetry, novelettes, short stories, plays, articles, book reviews; he is also the author of the novel Seven Yesterdays.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Paul Hoffman Papers consist primarily of Hoffman's Writings in typescript, manuscript, and printed and published form. These include poems, short stories, articles, and book reviews as well as fragments of his personal journal and some school and college papers. At the end of this series are a few photographs, clippings, and programs. Correspondence covers some thirty years and includes a small amount of miscellanea (printed material, programs).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has received minimal processing and remains largely in original order. The first two boxes of short stories are in alphabetical order by title, but the material in the remaining boxes is in no particular order.
Related Material
has made a concerted effort over the years to ensure that its manuscript and rare books holdings complement each other. As a result, many of our manuscript collections are supported by books, pamphlets, serials and other items which are cataloged in the Rare Books Collection. Please be sure to search for these related materials.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Hoffman, Paul -- Archives.; American literature -- 20th century.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Novelists, American.; Poets, American.; Book reviews.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Juvenilia.; Manuscripts for publication.; Notebooks.; Photographs.; Poems.; Authors.; Novelists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Writings
  - "As Between Bostonians", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 7 pages; short story, typed, 6 pages; short story, typed with pencil corrections, 6 pages (Box 1)
  - "Blood of the Lamb", short story, typed, 6 pages (Box 1)
  - "At Bohm's and Later", short story, typed with ink corrections, 7 pages; short story, typed, 7 pgs. (Box 1)
  - "A Chance Meeting", short story, typed, 9 pages; short story, typed with pencil corrections, 8 pages (Box 1)
  - "A Cheerful Story", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 9 pages (Box 1)
  - "Death and the Maidens", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 6 pages; short story, typed with ink corrections, 5 pages; a short story by Martha Lawrence, typed, 6 pages (Box 1)
  - Folksong at Yetta's, novelette, typed with pencil corrections, 78 pages (Box 1)
  - The Gates of the Sky, novelette, typed, 93 pages (Box 1)
  - "The Gay One", short story, (plus 1 copy) typed, 20 pages (Box 1)
  - "German Day", short story, typed, 11 pages "German Day" a short story, typed, 11 pages "German Day" a short story, typed, 16 pages (Box 1)
  - "The Green Thumb of Willard Speck", short story, typed 30 pages (Box 1)
  - "Grow Old Along with Me", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 11 pages; short story, typed, 11 pages; short story, typed, 21 pages; typed copy, 21 pages (Box 1)
  - "Juliet Was Fourteen", short story, typed with ink corrections, 10 pages (Box 1)
  - "Imitation of Love", short story, 21 pages (Box 1)
  - Light and Shadow, novelette, typed, 44 pages (Box 1)
  - "Interrupted Morning", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 31 pages; typed, 32 pages; typed, 15 pages; typed, 16 pages (Box 1)
  - "Lost Art", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 18 pages (Box 1)
  - "Mildred Mary Orr", a story for True Story Magazine, typed, 20 pages; typed, 38 pages (Box 1)
  - "The Modest Amazon", short story, typed, 25 pages; typed, 24 pages (Box 1)
  - "The Most Unforgettable Character", typed, 13 pages (Box 1)
  - "Mrs. Mulrooney makes a Speech", typed, (plus 2 copies) - 13 pages (Box 2)
  - "Old Home Week", short story, typed, 21 pages (Box 2)
  - "Picking a Winner", short story, typed, 5 pages (Box 2)
  - "Pick-up In the Park", a synopsis typed with pencil corrections, 10 pages (Box 2)
  - Story based an Questionnaire of Mrs. Walter J. Zebb, typed 10 pages, also 2 draft copies - 10 pages (Box 2)
  - Questionnaire from Mrs. Sylvia Neel, a story 26 pages (Box 2)
  - "A Resemblance To Fame", short story, typed, 41 pages; re-write, typed with pencil corrections, 30 pages (Box 2)
  - "Sacrament", short story, typed, 6 pages (Box 2)
  - "Sandy Claws Wedding Ring Wyoming", short story, typed with ink corrections, 22 pages (Box 2)
  - "Sense of Time", short story (2 copies) with pencil corrections, 14 pages (Box 2)
  - "A Sign in the Sky", short story (1 copy), typed, 21 p. (Box 2)
  - "Slaughter of an Innocent", short story, (1 copy), typed 6 pages (Box 2)
  - "Surprise for Willie", short story, (plus 2 copies), typed, 10 pages (Box 2)
  - "The Long Ago", short story,, (1 copy), typed, 21 pages (Box 2)
  - "The Street and the People", (1 copy), typed, 20 pages (Box 2)
  - "The Trip", short story, typed, 20 pages, plus 1 copy, typed, with pencil corrections, 19 pages (Box 2)
  - The Use of Love or Come, Let Us Kiss and Part, novelette (plus 2 copies) typed, 48 pages (Box 2)
  - "Toby", short story, (plus 1 copy), typed, 5 pg. (Box 2)
  - "Voyage of Rediscovery", short story, typed, 22 pages (Box 2)
  - "What Would I Do Without You?", short story, typed, 22 p. plus copy, typed with corrections (pencil), 27 pages (Box 2)
  - English notebook, in short hand, 52 pages (Box 3)
  - Comparative Literature II class notebook, in shorthand, 114 pages (Box 3)
  - Record book containing class notes, in shorthand, 71 pages (Box 3)
  - The United States of America vs. Two Oil Paintings Et Al", mss. typed, 18 pages (Box 3)
  - "The Protégés and Escorts", typed section of a chapter, 9 pages (Box 3)
  - Sketch for a preface - (Gardner Biography) (Box 3)
  - "Country Christmas - A Reminiscence", typed, 17 pages (Box 3)
  - "Love is Blind", typed, short story, 7 pages (Box 3)
  - "Act One, Scene One", typed, 7 pages (Box 3)
  - "The Strange Tea Party", typed, 9 pages (plus 1 copy) (Box 3)
  - "Jubilee", typed, 23 pages (Box 3)
  - "Family Portrait", typed, 9 pages (Box 3)
  - "The Street and the People", typed short story, 20 pages (Box 3)
  - "Elizabeth", typed, 13 pages, (plus 1 copy) (Box 3)
  - "Greek God Williams", typed short story, 6 pages (Box 3)
  - "Lost Art", typed short story, 19 pages (Box 3)
  - At Yetta's, novelette, typed, 83 pages (Box 3)
  - Folksong, a novelette, typed, 83 pages (Box 4)
  - "A Study of the Role of the Moon in the Poems of Samuel Taylor Coleridge", typed, 16 pages (English class paper), plus 1 copy (Box 4)
  - "Mr. Turk and Miss Hammer", typed, 17 pages (Box 4)
  - Mr. Ingalls", short story, typed, 23 pages (Box 4)
  - "Love Story", short story, typed plus 1 copy, 6 pages (Box 4)
  - "Sense of Time", short story, typed, 4 pages (Box 4)
  - "Brave Farewell", short story (plus 2 copies), typed, 9 pages (Box 4)
  - "Touché", short story (plus 1 copy), typed, 8 pages (Box 4)
  - "Mud Time", short story, typed 21 pages plus 1 copy (Box 4)
  - "All Dressed Up and No Place to Go", short story typed 25 pages (Box 4)
  - "Dutchy", short story, typed, 18 pages plus 1 copy (Box 4)
  - "Choir Rehearsal", short story, typed, 21 pages (Box 4)
  - "No Turncoats", short story, typed, 22 pages (plus 1 copy) (Box 4)
  - "Conversation Piece", short story, typed, 5 pages (Box 4)
  - "Lottie", short story, typed, 19 pages (plus 1 copy) (Box 4)
  - "Nur Wer Die Sehnsucht Kennt", short story, typed, 8 pages. plus 1 copy (Box 4)
  - "She Walks in Beauty", short story, typed, 22 pages (Box 4)
  - "Long Distance Love", short story, typed, 9 pages (Box 4)
  - "Boston Piece", short story, (plus 2 copies) (Box 4)
  - "Different", short story, typed, 4 pages (Box 4)
  - "Old Amy", short story, typed, 11 pages (Box 4)
  - "Late Love", short story, typed, 26 pages (Box 4)
  - "Chippy", short story, typed, 21 pages plus 1 copy (Box 4)
  - "Juliet Was Fourteen", short story, typed, 10 pages (Box 4)
  - Seven Yesterdays, novel, 3 galleys (Box 4)
  - Seven Days Young, novel, typed 152 pages (Box 5)
  - "Tart But Not Sour", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 4 pages + 1 copy, 5 pages (Box 5)
  - "Dude Girl", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 35 pages plus one copy typed 36 pages (Box 5)
  - "But For the Grace of God", short story, typed with pencil corrections, 14 pages (Box 5)
  - "De Senectute", short story, typed with ink corrections, 5 pages (Box 5)
  - "They called Him Tough", short story, typed, 3 pages (Box 5)
  - "Bean and Belle", short story, typed, 2 pages (Box 5)
  - "The Dove of Peace", short story, typed, 3 pages (Box 5)
  - Unfinished novelettes, A. Untitled, typed with pencil corrections 59 pages B. Untitled, typed with pencil corrections 96 pages (Box 5)
  - Untitled prose mss., all typed, 12 potential short stories (Box 5)
  - Poetry (Box 5)
    Poems are:
    1. "Amaryllis" by Gardner Banker, holograph signed, 1 page
    2. "A Sonnet to Science," holograph, 6 pages
    3. "Biology A," typed, 1 page
    4. "Convenience Readymade," holograph, 1 page
    5. "De Profundis," typed, 1 page
    6. "Empty Glass," holograph, 1 page
    7. "Every Man to Other Men," typed, 2 pages
    8. "Feuille l'Automne," holograph, 1 page
    9. "For Yehudi Menuhin..." typed 1 page
    10. "The Gills of Inland," holograph, 1 page
    11. "Hagar's Lament," holograph, 1 page
    12. "Hamlet Redivivous," typed, 6 pages
    13. "In Defiance of Big Business, typed, 2 pages
    14. "In Memoriam," typed, 1 page
    15. "Judith," typed, 2 pages
    16. "Little Go-Flop," holograph, 6 pages
    17. "Lonely" typed, 1 page
    18. "Loneliness," typed, 1. page
    19. "Masque" typed, 10 pages
    20. "Mom" typed, 2 pages
    21. "To Nazimova," typed, 1 page plus 1 copy
    22. "Now and Then,”‘ typed, 3 pages
    23. "Outcast," typed 2 pages
    24. "Remorse," holograph, 1 page
    25. "Rencontre," holograph, 1 page
    26. "Sense of Time," holograph and typed, 6 pages
    27. "Serenade," typed, 2 pages
    28. "Solstice," typed, 1 page
    29. "Song of the Machine," typed, 2 pages (3 copies)
    30. "Souvenir," 1 typed copy, 1 holograph copy 1 page each
    31. "Still Life," typed and holograph, 4 pages
    32. "Talisman" typed, 2 copies, 3 pages
    33. "Third Quarter, typed, 1 page
    34. "Talking To A Turnip," typed, 2 pages
    35. "The Children of Moscow," typed, 1 page
    36. "Three-Quarters Moon, typed, 1 page
    37. "To Marjorie an Christmas," typed, 1 page
    38. "Tomorrow," typed, 4 pages
    39. "To the Wind in the Chimney," typed, 1 page
    40. "To William Stiz," holograph, 1 page
    41. "Tristan..." typed, 1 page
    42. "Wisdom," printed galley, 1 page
    43. "Zweat," holograph, 2 pages
  - Personal journal, 1929-1930; 11 random pages (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous prose sheets, 222 pages (Box 5)
  - Untitled sheets of poetry, 61 pages (Box 6)
  - Town Topics of the Mohawk Valley, book review of Seven Yesterdays, Sept. 1933; 15 pages (Box 6)
  - Fiction Parade, "Mud Time," a poem by Paul Hoffman, March 1937; 594 pages (Box 6)
  - "Pick-up in the Dark," True Story, May, 1949; 25 pages (Box 6)
  - True Story, July 1949 (Box 6)
  - Theatre Magazine, Jan. 1926 (Box 6)
  - Theatre Magazine, August, 1923 (Box 6)
  - Harper's Bazaar, "Sense of Time", Sept. 15, 1937; poem by Hoffman, 136 pages (Box 6)
  - Harper's Bazaar, "The Bad One", April 1934; short story, 96 pages, plus 1 copy (Box 6)
  - "Ever After," Good Housekeeping, Aug. 1949; 49 pages (Box 6)
  - Printed book reviews by Hoffman (Box 6)
    1). "The Burning Cactus, by Stephen Spender
    2). "High Spaces" (on Theatre by Somerset Maugham)
    3). "The Short Story"
    4). Of Time and the River, by Thomas Wolfe
  - College papers and themes, October 6, 1928 - May 2, 1932; Harvard, 36 themes (Box 6)
  - Class notes and sketches, 84 pages (Box 6)
  - Publications, 3 Harvard Examinations; 1 Anglo-Saxon Primer (Box 6)
  - Class papers and themes, March - November 1942; Utica Free Academy, 16 essays (Box 6)
  - Photographs, Hoffman, family, home, Denver vacation & Europe; 31 photographs (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 14 Simplified piano pieces from C.W. Krogmann, the composer; 1 record, "Our Ethical Impasse," an oration by Paul Hoffman (Box 7)
  - Short plays (Box 7)
    1). The Chaste Adventures of Joseph by Floyd Dell, 16 pages
    2). Moonlight At the Crossroads, by J.M. Ross, 18 pages
  - The Players, 6 programs (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous programs & clippings (Box 7)
- Correspondence (Box 8)
  - 1920-1933, 49 incoming letters (Box 8)
  - 1934-1935, 7 incoming letters (Box 8)
  - 1936, 37 incoming letters (Box 8)
  - 1937-1938, 73 incoming letters (Box 8)
  - 1945-1953, 74 incoming letters (Box 8)
  - Undated letters and those not written to Hoffman, 62 letters (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    2 copies of Story Digest, July 1946
    1 copy of This Is Beloved, by Walter Benton
    1 class day week program
    1 Dance Program